GROMACS installation guide

1 Building GROMACS
2 Prerequisites

2.1 Platform
2.2 Compiler

2.2.1 Running in parallel

2.3 CMake
2.4 Fast Fourier Transform library

2.4.1 FFTW
2.4.2 MKL

2.5 Optional build components

3 Doing a build of GROMACS

3.1 Configuring with CMake
3.2 Using CMake command-line options
3.3 CMake advanced options
3.4 Helping CMake find the right libraries/headers/programs
3.5 CMake advice during the GROMACS 4.6 beta phase
3.6 Native GPU acceleration
3.7 Static linking
3.8 Suffixes for binaries and libraries
3.9 Building GROMACS
3.10 Installing GROMACS
3.11 Getting access to GROMACS after installation
3.12 Testing GROMACS for correctness
3.13 Testing GROMACS for performance
3.14 Having difficulty?

4 Special instructions for some platforms

4.1 Building on Windows
4.2 Building on Cray
4.3 Building on BlueGene

4.3.1 BlueGene/P
4.3.2 BlueGene/Q

5 Tested platforms
6 Other issues

GROMACS installation guide

1. Building GROMACS

These instructions pertain to building GROMACS 4.6 beta releases and newer. For installations instructions for old GROMACS versions, see here http://www.gromacs.org/Documentation/Installation_Instructions_4.5.

2. Prerequisites

2.1. Platform

GROMACS can be compiled for any distribution of Linux, Mac OS X, Windows (native, Cygwin or MinGW), BlueGene, Cray and probably others. Technically, it can be compiled on any platform with an ANSI C compiler and supporting libraries, such as the GNU C library. It can even compile on an iPhone! Later, there will be a detailed list of hardware, platform and compilers upon which we do build and regression testing.

2.2. Compiler

GROMACS requires an ANSI C compiler that complies with the C89 standard. For best performance, the GROMACS team strongly recommends you get the most recent version of your preferred compiler for your platform (e.g. GCC 4.7 or Intel 12.0 or newer on x86 hardware). There is a large amount of GROMACS code introduced in version 4.6 that depends on effective compiler optimization to get high performance - the old assembly-language routines have all gone. For other platforms, use the vendor's compiler, and check for specialized information below.

2.2.1. Running in parallel

GROMACS can run in parallel on multiple cores of a single workstation using its built-in ThreadMPI. No user action is required in order to enable this.

If you wish to use the excellent new native GPU support in GROMACS, NVIDIA's CUDA http://www.nvidia.com/object/cuda_home_new.html version 3.2 software development kit is required, and the latest version is encouraged. NVIDIA GPUs with at least NVIDIA compute capability 2.0 are required, e.g. Fermi or Kepler cards.

The GPU support from GROMACS version 4.5 using OpenMM https://simtk.org/home/openmm is still available, also requires CUDA, and remains the only hardware-based acceleration available for implicit solvent simulations in GROMACS. This parallelization path may not be maintained in the future.

If you wish to run in parallel on multiple machines across a network, you will need to have

an MPI library installed that supports the MPI 1.3 standard, and

wrapper compilers that will compile code using that library.

The GROMACS team recommends OpenMPI http://www.open-mpi.org/ version 1.4.1 (or higher), MPICH http://www.mpich.org/ version 1.4.1 (or higher), or your hardware vendor's MPI installation. The most recent version of either of this is likely to be the best. LAM/MPI http://www.lam-mpi.org/ may work, but since it has been deprecated for years, it is not supported.

In some cases, OpenMP parallelism is an advantage for GROMACS, but support for this is generally built into your compiler and you need to make no advance preparation for this. The performance gain you might achieve can vary with the compiler.

It is important to examine how you will use GROMACS and upon what hardware and with what compilers in deciding which parallelization paths to make available. Testing the performance of different options is unfortunately mandatory. The days of being able to just build and run 'mdrun' and get decent performance by default on your hardware are long gone. GROMACS will always run correctly, and does a decent job of trying to maximize your performance, but if you want to approach close to the optimum, you will need to do some work for it!

2.3. CMake

From version 4.6, GROMACS has moved to use the build system CMake. The previous build system that used configure from the GNU autotools package has been removed permanently. CMake permits the GROMACS team to support a very wide range of hardware, compilers and build configurations while continuing to provide the portability, robustness and performance for which GROMACS is known.

GROMACS requires CMake version 2.8.0 or higher. Lower versions will not work. You can check whether CMake is installed, and what version it is, with cmake --version. If you need to install CMake, then first check whether your platform's package management system provides a suitable version, or visit http://www.cmake.org/cmake/help/install.html for pre-compiled binaries, source code and installation instructions. The GROMACS team recommends you install the most recent version of CMake you can.

2.4. Fast Fourier Transform library

Many simulations in GROMACS make extensive use of Fourier transforms, and a software library to perform these is always required. We recommend FFTW http://www.fftw.org/ (version 3 or higher only) or Intel's MKL http://software.intel.com/en-us/intel-mkl.

2.4.1. FFTW

FFTW is likely to be available for your platform via its package management system, but there can be compatibility and significant performance issues associated with these packages. In particular, GROMACS simulations are normally run in single floating-point precision whereas the default FFTW package is normally in double precision, and good compiler options to use for FFTW when linked to GROMACS may not have been used. Accordingly, the GROMACS team recommends either

that you permit the GROMACS installation to download and build FFTW 3.3.2 from source automatically for you, or

that you build FFTW from the source code.

If you build FFTW from source yourself, get the most recent version and follow its installation guide (e.g. http://www.fftw.org/fftw3_doc/Installation-and-Customization.html). Choose the precision (i.e. single or float vs double) to match what you will later require for GROMACS. There is no need to compile with threading or MPI support, but it does no harm. On x86 hardware, compile only with --enable-sse2 (regardless of precision) even if your processors can take advantage of AVX extensions to SSE. The way GROMACS uses Fourier transforms cannot take advantage of this feature in FFTW because of memory system performance limitations, it can degrade performance by around 20%, and there is no way for GROMACS to require the use of the SSE2 at run time if AVX support has been compiled into FFTW.

2.4.2. MKL

Using MKL requires a set of linker flags that GROMACS is not able to detect for you, so setting up optimal linking is tricky at the moment. Need better documentation later.

2.5. Optional build components

A hardware-optimized BLAS or LAPACK library is useful for some of the GROMACS utilities, but is not needed for running simulations.

The built-in GROMACS trajectory viewer ngmx requires X11 and Motif/Lesstif libraries and header files. Generally, the GROMACS team recommends you use third-party software for visualization, such as VMD http://www.ks.uiuc.edu/Research/vmd/ or PyMOL http://www.pymol.org/.

3. Doing a build of GROMACS

This section will cover a general build of GROMACS with CMake, but it is not an exhaustive discussion of how to use CMake. There are many resources available on the web, which we suggest you search for when you encounter problems not covered here. The material below applies specifically to builds on Unix-like systems, including Linux, Mac OS X, MinGW and Cygwin. For other platforms, see the specialist instructions below.

3.1. Configuring with CMake

CMake will run many tests on your system and do its best to work out how to build GROMACS for you. If you are building GROMACS on hardware that is identical to that where you will run mdrun, then you can be sure that the defaults will be pretty good. Howver, if you want to control aspects of the build, there's plenty of things you can set, too.

The best way to use CMake to configure GROMACS is to do an “out-of-source” build, by making another directory from which you will run CMake. This can be a subdirectory or not, it doesn't matter. It also means you can never corrupt your source code by trying to build it! So, the only required argument on the CMake command line is the name of the directory containing the CMakeLists.txt file of the code you want to build. For example, download the source tarball and use

$ tar xfz gromacs-4.6-beta1-src.tgz
$ cd gromacs-4.6-beta1
$ mkdir build-cmake
$ cd build-cmake
$ cmake ..

You will see cmake report the results of a large number of tests on your system made by CMake and by GROMACS. These are written to the CMake cache, kept in CMakeCache.txt. You can edit this file by hand, but this is not recommended because it is easy to reach an inconsistent state. You should not attempt to move or copy this file to do another build, because the paths are hard-coded within it. If you mess things up, just delete this file and start again with 'cmake'.

If there's a serious problem detected at this stage, then you will see a fatal error and some suggestions for how to overcome it. If you're not sure how to deal with that, please start by searching on the web (most computer problems already have known solutions!) and then consult the gmx-users mailing list. There are also informational warnings that you might like to take on board or not. Piping the output of cmake through less or tee can be useful, too.

CMake works in an iterative fashion, re-running each time a setting is changed to try to make sure other things are consistent. Once things seem consistent, the iterations stop. Once cmake returns, you can see all the settings that were chosen and information about them by using

$ ccmake ..

Check out http://www.cmake.org/cmake/help/runningcmake.html for general advice on what you are seeing and how to navigate and change things. The settings you might normally want to change are already presented. If you make any changes, then ccmake will notice that and require that you re-configure (using 'c'), so that it gets a chance to make changes that depend on yours and perform more checking. This might require several configuration stages when you are using ccmake - when you are using cmake the iteration is done behind the scenes.

A key thing to consider here is the setting of GMX_INSTALL_PREFIX. You will need to be able to write to this directory in order to install GROMACS later, and if you change your mind later, changing it in the cache triggers a full re-build, unfortunately. So if you do not have super-user privileges on your machine, then you will need to choose a sensible location within your home directory for your GROMACS installation.

When cmake or ccmake have completed iterating, the cache is stable and a build tree can be generated, with 'g' in ccmake or automatically with cmake.

3.2. Using CMake command-line options

Once you become comfortable with setting and changing options, you may know in advance how you will configure GROMACS. If so, you can speed things up by invoking cmake with a command like:

$ cmake .. -DGMX_GPU=ON -DGMX_MPI=ON -DGMX_INSTALL_PREFIX=/home/marydoe/programs

to build with GPUs, MPI and install in a custom location. You can even save that in a shell script to make it even easier next time. You can also do this kind of thing with ccmake, but you should avoid this, because the options set with '-D' will not be able to be changed interactively in that run of ccmake.

3.3. CMake advanced options

The options that can be seen with ccmake are ones that we think a reasonable number of users might want to consider changing. There are a lot more options available, which you can see by toggling the advanced mode in ccmake on and off with 't'. Even there, most of the variables that you might want to change have a 'CMAKE_' or 'GMX_' prefix.

3.4. Helping CMake find the right libraries/headers/programs

If libraries are installed in non-default locations their location can be specified using the following environment variables:

CMAKE_INCLUDE_PATH for header files

CMAKE_LIBRARY_PATH for libraries

CMAKE_PREFIX_PATH for header, libraries and binaries (e.g. '/usr/local').

The respective 'include', 'lib', or 'bin' is appended to the path. For each of these variables, a list of paths can be specified (on Unix seperated with ”:”). Note that these are enviroment variables (and not CMake command-line arguments) and in a 'bash' shell are used like:

$ CMAKE_PREFIX_PATH=/opt/fftw:/opt/cuda cmake ..

The CC and CXX environment variables are also useful for indicating to CMake which compilers to use, which can be very important for maximising GROMACS performance. Similarly, CFLAGS/CXXFLAGS can be used to pass compiler options, but note that these will be appended to those set by GROMACS for your build platform and build type. You can customize some of this with advanced options such as CMAKE_C_FLAGS and its relatives.

See also: http://cmake.org/Wiki/CMake_Useful_Variables#Environment_Variables

3.5. CMake advice during the GROMACS 4.6 beta phase

We'd like users to have the ability to change any setting and still have the CMake cache stable; ie. not have things you set mysteriously change, or (worse) the whole thing breaks. We're not there yet. If you know in advance you will want to use a particular setting, set that on the initial cmake command line. If you have to change compilers, do that there, or immediately afterwards in ccmake. Gross changes like GPU or shared libraries on/off are more likely to work if you do them on the initial command line, because that's how we've been doing it while developing and testing. If you do make a mess of things, there's a great thing about an out-of-source build - you can just do 'rm -rf *' and start again. Easy!

We are interested in learning how you managed to break things. If you can reproducibly reach a state where CMake can't proceed, or subsequent compilation/linking/running fails, then we need to know so we can fix it!

3.6. Native GPU acceleration

If you have the CUDA SDK installed, you can use CMake with:

cmake .. -DGMX_GPU=ON -DCUDA_TOOLKIT_ROOT_DIR=/usr/local/cuda

(or whichever path has your installation). Note that this will require a working C++ compiler, and in some cases you might need to handle this manually, e.g. with the advanced option CUDA_HOST_COMPILER.

More documentation needed here - particular discussion of fiddly details on Windows, Linux and Mac required. Not all compilers on all systems can be made to work.

3.7. Static linking

Dynamic linking of the GROMACS executables will lead to a smaller disk footprint when installed, and so is the default. However, on some hardware or under some circumstances you might need to do static linking. To link GROMACS binaries statically against the internal GROMACS libraries, set BUILD_SHARED_LIBS=OFF. To link statically against external libraries as well, the GMX_PREFER_STATIC_LIBS=ON option can be used. Note, that in general CMake picks up whatever is available, so this option only instructs CMake to prefer static libraries when both static and shared are available. If no static version of an external library is available, even when the aforementioned option is ON, the shared library will be used. Also note, that the resulting binaries will still be dynamically linked against system libraries if that is all that is available.

3.8. Suffixes for binaries and libraries

It is sometimes convenient to have different versions of the same GROMACS libraries installed. The most common use cases have been single and double precision, and with and without MPI. By default, GROMACS will suffix binaries and libraries for such builds with '_d' for double precision and/or '_mpi' for MPI (and nothing otherwise). This can be controlled manually with GMX_DEFAULT_SUFFIX, GMX_BINARY_SUFFIX and GMX_LIBRARY_SUFFIX.

3.9. Building GROMACS

Once you have a stable cache, you can build GROMACS. If you're not sure the cache is stable, you can re-run cmake .. or ccmake ..' to see. Then you can run make to start the compilation. Before actual compilation starts, make checks that the cache is stable, so if it isn't you will see CMake run again.

So long as any changes you've made to the configuration are sensible, it is expected that the make procedure will always complete successfully. The tests GROMACS makes on the settings you choose are pretty extensive, but there are probably a few cases we haven't thought of yet. Search the web first for solutions to problems, but if you need help, ask on gmx-users, being sure to provide as much information as possible about what you did, the system you are building on, and what went wrong.

If you have a multi-core or multi-CPU machine with N processors, then using

$ make -j N

will generally speed things up by quite a bit.

3.10. Installing GROMACS

Finally, make install will install GROMACS in the directory given in GMX_INSTALL_PREFIX. If this is an system directory, then you will need permission to write there, and you should use super-user privileges only for make install and not the whole procedure.

3.11. Getting access to GROMACS after installation

GROMACS installs the script GMXRC in the bin subdirectory of the installation directory (e.g. /usr/local/gromacs/bin/GMXRC), which you should source from your shell:

$ source your-installation-prefix-here/bin/GMXRC

It will detect what kind of shell you are running and set up your environment for using GROMACS. You may wish to arrange for your login scripts to do this automatically; please search the web for instructions on how to do this for your shell.

3.12. Testing GROMACS for correctness

TODO install and use regression set

3.13. Testing GROMACS for performance

TODO benchmarks

3.14. Having difficulty?

You're not alone, this can be a complex task. If you encounter a problem with installing GROMACS, then there are a number of locations where you can find assistance. It is recommended that you follow these steps to find the solution:

Read the installation instructions again, taking note that you have followed each and every step correctly.

Search the GROMACS website and users emailing list for information on the error.

Search the internet using a search engine such as Google.

Post to the GROMACS users emailing list gmx-users for assistance. Be sure to give a full description of what you have done and why you think it didn't work. Give details about the system on which you are installing. Copy and paste your command line and as much of the output as you think might be relevant - certainly from the first indication of a problem. Describe the machine and operating system you are running on. People who might volunteer to help you do not have time to ask you interactive detailed follow-up questions, so you will get an answer faster if you provide as much information as you think could possibly help.

4. Special instructions for some platforms

4.1. Building on Windows

Building on Cygwin/MinGW/etc. works just like Unix. Please see the instructions above.

Building on Windows using native compilers is rather similar to building on Unix, so please start by reading the above. Then, download and unpack the GROMACS source archive. The UNIX-standard .tar.gz format can be managed on Windows, but you may prefer to browse ftp://ftp.gromacs.org/pub/gromacs to obtain a .zip format file, which doesn't need any external tools to unzip on recent Windows systems. Make a folder in which to do the out-of-source build of GROMACS. For example, make it within the folder unpacked from the source archive, and call it “build-cmake”.

Next, you need to open a command shell. If you do this from within your IDE (e.g. Microsoft Visual Studio), it will configure the environment for you. If you use a normal Windows command shell, then you will need to either set up the environment to find your compilers and libraries yourself, or run the vcvarsall.bat batch script provided by MSVC (just like sourcing a bash script under Unix). Presumably Intel's IDE has a similar functionality.

Within that command shell, change to the folder you created above. Run cmake .., where the folder you point CMake towards is the folder created by the GROMACS installer. Resolve issues as above. You will probably make your life easier and faster by using the new facility to download and install FFTW automatically. After the initial run of cmake, you may wish to use cmake, ccmake or the GUI version of CMake until your configuration is complete.

To compile GROMACS, you then use cmake --build . so the right tools get used.

4.2. Building on Cray

Probably you need to build static libraries only? Volunteer needed.

4.3. Building on BlueGene

4.3.1. BlueGene/P

Mark to write later. There is currently no native acceleration on this platform, but the default plain C kernels will work.

4.3.2. BlueGene/Q

Mark to write later. There is currently no native acceleration on this platform, but the default plain C kernels will work.

5. Tested platforms

While it is our best belief that GROMACS will build and run pretty much everywhere, it's important that we tell you where we really know it works because we've tested it. We do test on Linux, Windows, and Mac with a range of compilers and libraries for a range of our configuration options. Every commit in our git source code repository is tested on … We test irregularly on…

Contributions to this section are welcome.

Later we might set up the ability for users to contribute test results to Jenkins.

6. Other issues

The GROMACS utility programs often write data files in formats suitable for the Grace plotting tool, but it is straightforward to use these files in other plotting programs, too.